<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0">
  <info>
    <title>OpenCards Manual</title>
    <subtitle>A free flashcard learning extension for OpenOffice Impress</subtitle>
    <author><personname>The OpenCards project and contributors</personname></author>
  </info>
  <!--
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/oclogo.png" align="center"/></imageobject>
  </mediaobject>-->
  <para><code>This document becomes extended on request only, and is therefore based on your and
      only your needs. So if you consider a part of OpenCards to be not or insufficiently
      documented, you're welcome to drop us note with your questions, remarks and ideas in our <link
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
        xlink:href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/?group_id=198974">support forums</link> at
      sourceforge. </code></para>
  <sect1>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>OpenOffice Impress allows to compile, communicate and explain complex facts and figures
      via visually attractive presentations. However, it lacks of means to keep all these these
      greatly visualized and condensed information in mind. OpenCards attempts to fill this gap by
      attaching a memorization layer to OpenOffice. </para>
    <para>OpenCards is a BSD-style licensed flashcard learning extension for OpenOffice Impress. The
      basic idea of OpenCards is to use slide-titles as flashcard fronts and the slide contents as
      their backs (cf. figure 1). Based on state-of-the-art memorization and scheduling algorithms
      OpenCards will help you to learn any set of flashcards. </para>
    <para>There are many flashcard learning applications available. Some of them implement fancy
      learning techniques, some of them look very polished, but almost all of them lack of one
      essential feature: Flexible, intuitive flashcard creation. In many cases, competing products
      support simple text cards only. Additionally, we're not aware of any competing product that
      builds on a standardized document format. With OpenCards we've tried to overcome these
      limitations by just plugging well-established learning and memorization methods into one of
      the best free office applications available: OpenOffice Impress. </para>
    <para>Being an extension for OpenOffice Impress, OpenCards gives you any freedom you enjoy when
      creating OpenOffice Impress-slides. OpenCards just adds all functionality that turn any
      existing Impress/Powerpoint presentation on-the-fly into a set of flashcards. Furthermore, it
      comes along with tools necessary to manage large amounts of presentation-files. </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The basic idea of OpenCards</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="./figures/opencards-idea.png" align="center" scale="60"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>Education is the key-factor in the global struggle for economic and social success.
      OpenCards provides a flashcard learning extension for OpenOffice Impress, that makes Impress a
      unique solution for education. </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>OpenCards implements two different learning models. A box-based short-term learning
      procedure, also known as Leitner-learning1, and a more sophisticated long-term memorization
      model based on an improved version of the SM-2 algorithm2. Whereas the former is designed for
      to quickly cram large amounts of facts (e.g. in preparation to an examination), the latter
      (cf. Figure 2) predicts the user's memorization performance in order to maximize knowledge
      retention. Thereby it minimizes the time investment necessary to memorize tens, hundreds, or
      even thousands of facts. </para>
    <para>The learning states of the slides within an Impress-presentation are stored directly
      within the ODF meta-data model. This we consider to be a key feature of OpenCards, because it
      allows to learn a card-set in changing/shifting environments involving different computers or
      operating systems. </para>
    <figure>
      <title>The long-term memorization model of OpenCards</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="./figures/learning-curve.png" scale="80" align="center"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>During learning OpenCards presents scheduled slides to evaluate the users retention level.
      First only the card-question is being presented. Normally this will be the slide title, but
      OpenCards supports also other questioning modes. After the user has tried to recall the fact,
      she can give a feedback about her retention level (cf. Figure 3). Based on the reported
      retrieval-strength OpenCards will update the learning model of the current slide and
      reschedule it in an optimal manner. </para>
    <para>
      <figure>
        <title>OpenCards in action during a learning session</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="./figures/oc-in-action.png" align="center" scale="40"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Flashcard configuration</title>
    <para>Flashcards can be configured in various ways.</para>
    <para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/config-while-learning.png"
            scale="40"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject>
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>LastMinute memorization</title>
    <para>test test</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>LastMinute session preparation</title>
      <para>test test</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>LastMinute session learning</title>
      <para>During last minute learning you're given only two possible answers. If you know a
        flashcard you click <emphasis role="italic">Perfectly</emphasis>, otherwise you click on
          <emphasis role="italic">Not at all.</emphasis> In the former case the current card would
        be moved to the next higher box. In the latter case the card would be either moved to the
        first card box or to the next lower box (depending on how you've configured OpenCards. Cf.
        sectio</para>
      <para>During last-minute learning OpenCards shows a dynamically updated card box system. The
        current flashcard currently being processed is is indicated with red color. New so far
        unlearnt items are depectied as blue items. If you consider the card box view to be too
        distracting just try to resize the dialog window. If you've reached a certain small size the
        box view will dissappear.</para>
      <para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/lastmin-learndialog.png"
              align="center" scale="70"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>LongTerm memorization</title>
    <para>Beside its core learning model framework, OpenCards comes along with all necessary tools
      to manage large amount of flashcard-presentations. </para>
    <sect2>
      <title>The LTM-Manager</title>
      <para>The so called “Long-Term Memorization Manager” provides a tree based categorization
        interface that also comprises different statistics about current schedule and learning
        progress. Instead of opening all files of interest manually, the user just needs to select
        the category he want to refresh, and OpenCards will automatically determine the slides
        within this category scheduled for the current day. Subsequently, it will automatically
        iterate over all these items by opening the necessary files, navigating to the scheduled
        items and by evaluating your recall-ability as mentioned above. </para>
      <para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/ltm-manager.png" scale="50"
            /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
      <sect3>
        <title>Long term learning modes</title>
        <para>Basically there are three different learning modes when using OpenCards to learn
          things for a very long time<itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Scheduled Learning: This mode is the <emphasis role="bold">default</emphasis>
                mode and is used in alomst all cases. </para>
              <para>It is started when the "Start Learning"-button has been pressed in the
                LTM-Manager. Internally OpenCards will then collect all cards of the selected card
                files (or all current files if no files is selected) scheduled until today. To make
                sure that items are not forgotten if you've skipped your daily OpenCards quarted,
                this will also include items that were scheduled to a past date. </para>
              <para>All collected cards will be then presented in a file-wise manner: OpenCards
                iterates over all files containing at least one scheduled item and presents this for
                learinng/reviewing.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Refreshment: This mode becomes activated when the <keycap>Alt</keycap> is
                pressed before the "Start Learning"-button is about to be pressed. OpenCards will
                indicate the changed mode by altering the button label to "Start refreshing". When
                using this leanring scheme OpenCards presents not only scheduled items of the
                selected card files, but <emphasis role="italic">all</emphasis> items found in these
                files. This gives you the possibility to refresh your knowledge in immediate
                preparation to an exam. </para>
              <para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
                      fileref="figures/refresh-learning.png"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
              <para>If you score items with "well" or "perfectly" their internal state won't be
                changed at all. If your recall ability was less than "well" these items will be
                rescheduled accordingly.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>Force New Cards: This mode becomes activated when the <keycap>Ctrl</keycap> is
                pressed when the "Start Learning"-button is about to be pressed. OpenCards will
                indicate the changed mode by altering the button label to "Start Learning (+New)".
                Normally OpenCards restricts the number of new cards to be learnt according to your
                setting in <emphasis role="italic">Preferences->LTM Learning</emphasis> (default =
                30). But when using this scheme OpenCards will include all new itmes into the
                learning session to be instantiated.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
      </sect3>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>LTM Learning</title>
      <para>While iterating of the scheduled items you can either use your mouse to unhide complete
        cards or to rate your recall abilities. However, OpenCards implements a keyboard scheme that
        allows you to completly avoid the mouse while learning flashcards. This scheme is depicted
        below.</para>
      <para>
        <inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/keylayout-ltm-show.png"
              scale="70"/></imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject></para>
      <para><inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/keylayout-ltm-score.png"
              scale="70"/></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Preferences</title>
    <para>test tes </para>
  </sect1>
  <glossary/>
  <appendix>
    <info>
      <title>Frequently asked questions</title>
    </info>
    <sect1>
      <title>How to configure a single slide in a flashcard set?</title>
      <para>You can do via the context menu of the slide in the slide pane as depicted in the
        figure.</para>
      <para>.<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata fileref="figures/oc-cxtmenu.png" scale="50"
            /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
    </sect1>
  </appendix>
  <appendix>
    <title>License</title>
    <para>Copyright 2007-2008 Holger Brandl and contributors of the OpenCards-projects. All Rights
      Reserved. Use is subject to license terms. </para>
    <para>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are
      permitted provided that the following conditions are met: <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of
            conditions and the following disclaimer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list
            of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials
            provided with the distribution. 3. 4. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Original authors' names are not deleted.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>The authors' names are not used to endorse or promote products derived from this
            software without specific prior written permission.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist></para>
    <para>HOLGER BRANDL AND THE CONTRIBUTORS TO THIS WORK DISCLAIM ALL WARRANTIES WITH REGARD TO
      THIS SOFTWARE, INCLUDING ALL IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS. IN NO EVENT
      SHALL HOLGER BRANDL NOR THE CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY SPECIAL, INDIRECT OR CONSEQUENTIAL
      DAMAGES OR ANY DAMAGES WHATSOEVER RESULTING FROM LOSS OF USE, DATA OR PROFITS, WHETHER IN AN
      ACTION OF CONTRACT, NEGLIGENCE OR OTHER TORTIOUS ACTION, ARISING OUTOF OR IN CONNECTION WITH
      THE USE OR PERFORMANCE OF THIS SOFTWARE. </para>
  </appendix>
</article>
